A Guide to the Historic Hudson Valley records, Manuscript Collection FA796
Rockefeller Archive Center
Historic Hudson Valley records, Manuscript Collection
1585-1938
Rockefeller Archive Center
Historic Hudson Valley (Organization)
Sleepy Hollow Restorations (Organization)
FA796
0.27 Cubic Feet 27 microfilm reels (35mm).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited at the RAC by Sleepy Hollow Restorations in 1977, with an updated deposit by Historic Hudson Valley in 2024.
Scope and Contents
These manuscripts date mostly from the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries and relate to the Hudson River area in New York, specifically to the initial three historic sites owned by Historic Hudson Valley (formerly Sleepy Hollow Restorations): Sunnyside, the home of Washington Irving; Philipsburg Manor; and Van Cortland Manor.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in eight series by family.
- Washington Irving papers, 1585-1923; 1813-1865; 1; 0.13 Cubic Feet 13 microfilm reels (35mm); 366 items.
  Scope and Contents
  Personal and family material such as manuscripts, maps, notes, wills, passports, deeds, and correspondence. Also contains papers of the family of Irving's finace, Matilda Hoffman.
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 1)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 2)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 3)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 4)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 5)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 6)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 7)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 8)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 9)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 10)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 11)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 12)
  - Washington Irving papers (Reel 13)
- Philipse Family papers, 1683-1822; 2; 0.02 Cubic Feet 2 microfilm reels (35mm); 50 items.
  The legal and business papers of Philip Schuyler and members of his family.
  - Philipse Family papers (Reel 13)
  - Philipse Family papers (Reel 14)
- Hamilton Family papers, 1843; 3; 0.01 Cubic Feet 1 microfilm reel (35mm); 75 items
  Consists of letters to and from Alexander Hamilton III (1816-1889), some dating from his service as secretary of the U.S. Legation at Madrid during Washington Irving's tenure as minister to Spain.
  - Hamilton Family papers (Reel 14)
- Schuyler Family papers, 1729-1850; 4; 0.02 Cubic Feet 2 microfilm reels (35mm); 123 items.
  Correspondence, bills, covenants, and indentures of Philip Schuyler and members of his family.
  - Schuyler Family papers (Reel 15)
  - Schuyler Family papers (Reel 16)
- Beekman Family papers, 1721-1903; 5; 0.02 Cubic Feet 2 microfilm reels (35mm); 203 items.
  The legal and business papers of Henry and Gertrude Beekman, 18th century landowners and entrepreneurs, and the descendants of Gerard G. and Cornelia Beekman, 19th century owners of Philipsburg Manor.
  - Beekman Family papers (Reel 16)
  - Beekman Family papers (Reel 17)
- Chadeayne and Conklin Family papers, 1700-1859; 6; 0.01 Cubic Feet 1 microfilm reel (35mm); 29 items.
  Legal and business material, agreements, drafts, indentures, and deeds.
  - Chadeayne and Conklin Family papers (Reel 17)
- Van Cortland Family papers, 1661-1938; 1750-1840; 7; 0.07 Cubic Feet 7 microfilm reels (35mm); 1501 items.
  Comprised of correspondence, indentures, rent rolls, wills, account books, receipts, and cookbooks of members of the Van Cortland family, emphasizing the careers of Pierre Van Cortlandt (1721-1814) and his sons Philip (1749-1832) and Pierre, Jr. (1762-1848).
  - Van Cortland Family papers (Reel 17)
  - Van Cortland Family papers (Reel 18)
  - Van Cortland Family papers (Reel 23)
  - Van Cortland Family papers (Reel 24)
  - Van Cortland Family papers (Reel 25)
  - Van Cortland Family papers (Reel 26)
  - Van Cortland Family papers (Reel 27)
- Miscellaneous Documents, 1651-1903; 8; 0.05 Cubic Feet 5 microfilm reels (35mm); 394 items.
  Includes business and legal records, correspondence and autographs of literary and political figures, material on the Andre Monument in Tarrytown, NY, and on local Revolutionary War and Civil War figures.
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 19)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 21)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 22)